Fissha Seyoum Teshome

Arlington, Virginia, USA fiseyoum@gmail.com +15712778431

SUMMARY

Experienced in Information Technology Management with a demonstrated history of working in the higher education industry. Skilled within the Computer Science realm that include Java, C++, Android, Symbian C++, C#, javaScript, Jquery, Angular, MYSQL, MYSQL Server, Python, Node Js, REACT js, Software design, development, testing and other Programming languages. Strong information technology professional with Master's in Information Science (MSC) focused on Global Information Technology Management and a Bachelor of Engineering (BEng) focused on Computer Engineering, Software Engineering, Networking with CCNA, TeleCommunications, Computer Architecture, Electronics, Digital Image Processing, Digital circuits, Higher Engineering Mathematics and Physics, Programming, Information Sciences and Support Services additionally leadership, accounting, business management skills from Helsinki Metropolia University of Applied Sciences.

The Master's study was helpful to obtained knowledge in IT Governance in with the ISO and Cobit framework, Information systems project management, IT service management, Business continuance ,Responsible and sustainability business development, Enterprise Architecture, ICT service management and ITIL framework, Healthcare information systems management, cloud computing and SaaS, Big data analytics and Information Systems & Cybersecurity. This study was useful as it gave the opportunity to acquire managerial IT skills, project leadership, and knowledge in design, and implementation and service facilitation of IT. It has trained to design and implement business and working practices alignment together with users, experts, and managers. Furthermore, helpful in knowing the requirements of information systems and services together with the technical experts needed to implement them and obtain the desired business benefits. Last but least, skills in analyzing business strategy and organizational processes in the context of IT were obtained.

LINKS

- GitHub: https://github.com/Dev2050
- LinkedIn: https://fi.linkedin.com/in/fissha-seyoum-teshome-0b8b487

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF TURKU

Master's In Global Information Technology Management, GPA 4

Turku

Graduated 29 May 2017

In this Master's degree program, majoring in Information Systems, I studied the GITM program that gave me the opportunity to acquire managerial IT skills, project leadership, and knowledge in design, and implementation and service facilitation of IT. In the University, I was trained to design and implement business and working practices alignment together with users, experts, and managers. Furthermore, I have studied how to determine requirements of information systems and services together with the technical experts needed to implement them and obtain the desired business benefits. I have acquired skills in analyzing business strategy and organizational processes in the context of IT and obtained knowledge in IT governance, IT service management, business continuance, enterprise architecture, and cyber security.

Metropolia University of Applied Sciences

Bachelor of Engineering in Information Technology, GPA 3.95

Espoo

Graduated 29 April 2011

In this bachelor's program, I have been trained to become Computer Science and Information Technolgy Engineer. I have had the chance to acquire much of the IT skills that are from different areas of Computer Science fields. These Include Computer Architecture, Software Designing, Networking, Digital Circuits, Electronics, Real Time Operating Systems, Linux, Unix, and CISCO CCNA, Advanced Physics, and Mathematics for Computer Engineering dealing with probability and statistics. Additionally, skills in most of the object-oriented programming languages such as Java, C++, Android, Symbian C++ and C# and Algorithm & data structures. Other low-level programming languages such as C, Assembly languages, and Unix programming & web-based script languages namely, JavaScript, HTML, XML, CSS are also to mention.

Employment History

BSPSWAP

Software Engineer & CEO

Arlington Virginia

March 2019 -

Full stack software engineer and Chief Executive Officer (CEO) at Bspswap blockchain based company. Responsible for blockchain software development of Bspswap and Birrswap cryptocurrency exchange interfaces and the Bspswap cryptocurrency exchange platform. Additionally, the management and development of different community based platforms such as Jesus of Nazreth community platform.

I am coding, testing, and deploying these information systems projects. My roles also included, user interface designing, software system designing, writing smart contracts with solidity for BSP, BIRRC, BIRRS etc , and developing front-end and back-end systems of all projects.

Bspswap and Birrswap are cryptocurrency exchange interfaces working in parallel with the Bspswap exchange platform. Bspswap is also the name of the company that built the exchange platform and the interfaces. Birrswap is mainly dedicated to the Birr Money Exchange Service via https://birrswap.net. The Bspswap platform facilitates automated transactions between cryptocurrency tokens on the Ethereum, Binance or BSC, Polygon Matic, OKEx, XDai, Harmony, and Avalanche blockchains through the use of smart contracts.

Learn more about the company at https://bspswap.net and the platform at https://bspswap.com and https://birrswap.net.

DIGIA OY

Software Engineer

Helsinki

October – February 2019

Responsible for business software development named Digia Enterprise and involved in the processes of coding, testing, and deploying of this information systems. The major tasks included UI designing, software architecting the high-level structures of the software system and developing using Progress Openedge.

UNIVERSITY OF TURKU

Information Systems Management Researcher

Turku

May 2015 - May 2017

The focus of the research work is to develop an understanding of how visually impaired people face a digital disability divide. Its scope was limited to people with visual impairments who may or may not have access to technology. The research showed how to bridge the divide while exploring relevant topics that lead to the conception of feasible solutions. Further, it contributed to the development of more socially inclusive healthcare information systems. The research was supported by a thorough literature review of articles, journals, and research reports dealing with the major relevant topics. A qualitative research method was used to identify and obtain an in-depth understanding of the healthcare information accessibility (HCIA) barriers that visually impaired people face, and the factors involved in the creation of these barriers. Moreover, a quantitative method was used to collect primary data, and a number of different analysis methods were used to produce results. This led to findings that were generalized to the larger population of the visually impaired. The research shows that, despite the staggering advances in information and communication technology (ICT), the healthcare information needs of the visually impaired are not being met. However, it has also been discovered that the digital divide caused by visual impairment can be mitigated with intelligent design and the realization of information systems intended to fulfill the healthcare information needs of the visually impaired. A logical information system is needed that has a combination of input, back-end, and output assistive technologies with increased social inclusion and the capability to empower visually impaired people and help them access available healthcare information. The complete work of this thesis can be found at "http://www.grin.com/en/".

STUDYING AT THE UNIVERSITY OF TURKU

Global Information Technology Management Student

Turku

August 2013 – April 2015

This was the first year at the University of Turku and I was dealing with a number of interesting and professional IT managerial courses. The courses were demanding as they required a tangible effort and input from every student who really wanted to succeed.

SELF STUDYING AND LOOKING FOR OPPORTUNITIES

Programming languages

Helsinki

January 2012 – July 2013

During this period of unemployment caused due to the successful project completion, I kept myself busy with studying and looking for educational and job opportunities. I turned this gap to my own advantage by using it as an opportunity to study a number programming languages, frameworks, and different web development technologies. Mainly, I have learned PHP, JavaScript, jQuery, and Ajax frameworks.

TRACKER OY

Software Engineer

Oulunsalo

June 2010 – December 2011

Responsible for client software development named Ringi and involved in the processes of planning, creating, testing, and deploying of this information systems project. The major tasks included UI designing, software architecting the high-level structures of the software system, creating the structures, and also documentation of these structures. Further, programming and developing this software system using Android and Symbian C++

programmig languages, testing, and deploying it were my major responsibilities. Current status of the completed project can be found at "http://www.sunduka.com/".

METROPOLIA UNIVERSITY OF APPLIED SCIENCES

Software Developer

Espoo

May 2009 – January 2010

Tracking software development named Soft2050 was my major role. This software system, later on, served as the foundation for my Bachelor's thesis work. The work included programming this software system in Android, J2ME, and Symbian C++,testing, and deploying. Generally, all processes of planning, creating, testing, and deploying of this information systems project. The major tasks within the work included UI designing, software architecting the high-level structures of the software system, creating the structures, documentation of these structures including coding with Java Android, and also thesis report writing. The thesis report can be found at "https://www.theseus.fi/handle/10024/27420".

HOBBIES & INTERESTS

Software Engineering, programming, information systems sciences and computer science are my major hobbies. Learning new programming languages and following advancements in information systems management are my areas of interests.

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

Android: Advanced

Angular JS: TypeScript: Advaced

Java: Advanced

C++: Advanced

C: Intermediate

Node JS: Advanced

JavaScript: Advanced

C#: Advanced

.NET: Intermediate

XML: Advanced

CSS: Advanced

MySQL: Advanced

Python: Advanced

React js: Advanced

R Language: Advanced

Testing: Advanced

PHP: Advanced

HTML: Advanced

AJAX: Intermediate

MySQL Server: Intermediate

Cyber Security: Advanced

jQuery: Advanced

Eclipse: Advanced

Android Studio: Advanced

Netbeans: Advanced IT Strategy: Advanced

IT Service Management: Advanced

ITIL: Intermediate
Cobit: Intermediate

IT Operations: Advanced IT Outsourcing: Advanced

IT Security Management: Advanced

IT Infrastructure Management: Advanced

IT Audit: Intermediate

IT Governance: Advanced

IT Project & Program Management: Advanced

IT Service Delivery: Advanced Cloud Computing: Advanced Big Data Analytics: Intermediate

 $Enterprise\ Architecture: Advanced$

Progress Openedge: Advanced

Spring: Advanced AWS: Intermediate Spark: Advanced Scala: Advanced

LANGUAGES

English: Fluent Finnish: Fluent Amharic: Native

REFERENCES

Tuomas Harju

Employer at Tracker Oy

CTO at RTJ Group Oy

Oulu, Finland

URL: https://www.linkedin.com/in/tuomasharju/?ppe=1

Kalle Takkinen

Project manager at Tracker Oy

CTO at Satavision Oy

Oulu, Finland

URL: https://www.linkedin.com/in/kalle-takkinen-6babaa7/?ppe=1

Reima Suomi

Professor at Turku School of Economics

University of Turku

Turku, Finland

Email: reima.suomi@utu.fi

URL: https://fi.linkedin.com/in/reima-suomi-3b76135

Eija Koskivaara

Assistant professor at Turku School of Economics

University of Turku

Turku, Finland

Email: eija.koskivaara@utu.fi

URL: https://www.linkedin.com/in/eija-koskivaara-80269613/

Kari Salo

Department of Media Engineering

Helsinki Metropolia University of Applied Sciences

Email: kari.salo@metropolia.fi

Dr. Antti Piironen

Department of Information Technology

Helsinki Metropolia University of Applied Sciences

Telephone: +358 207 836403

Email: antti.piironen@metropolia.fi

Neeraj Sachdeva

Department of Information Systems

University of Turku

Turku, Finland

Email: neesac@utu.fi

Hannu Lohi

Tracker Oy

Employer at Tracker Oy

Oulunsalo, Finland

Email: hannu.lohi@trackersw.com

URL: https://www.linkedin.com/in/hannulohi/